So just by a show of hands, how many of you all have a robot at home?
ارفعوا أيديكم، كم منكم لديه روبوت في المنزل؟
Not very many of you.
ليس الكثير منكم.
Okay. And actually of those hands,
حسنا. ومن ضمن هذه الأيادي،
if you don't include Roomba how many of you have a robot at home?
إذا استثنينا رومبا كم منك لديه روبوت في المنزل؟
So a couple.
اثنان.
That's okay.
لا مشكلة.
That's the problem that we're trying to solve at Romotive --
هذه هي المشكلة التي نحاول حلها في Romotive --
that I and the other 20 nerds at Romotive are obsessed with solving.
أنا و20 مبدعا في Romotive مهوسون بايجاد حل لها.
So we really want to build a robot that anyone can use,
لذلك نريد بناء روبوت يستطيع أي أحد استخدامه،
whether you're eight or 80.
سواء كان عمره 8 سنوات أو 80 سنة.
And as it turns out, that's a really hard problem,
لكن اتضح ان هذه مشكلة صعبة
because you have to build a small, portable robot
لأنه عليك بناء روبوت صغير، محمول
that's not only really affordable,
ولا يكون غير مكلف ماديا فحسب،
but it has to be something
لكن يجب أن شيئا
that people actually want to take home and have around their kids.
يرغب الناس لأخذه للمنزل حول أطفالهم.
This robot can't be creepy or uncanny.
لايمكن لهذا الروبوت أن يكون مخيفا او غريبا.
He should be friendly and cute.
يجب أن يكون وديا و وجذابا.
So meet Romo.
تعرفوا على رومو.
Romo's a robot that uses a device you already know and love --
رومو هو روبوت يستخدم جهاز تعرفه وتحبه --
your iPhone -- as his brain.
جهاز الآيفون -- كدماغ.
And by leveraging the power of the iPhone's processor,
وبتسخير قوة معالج الآيفون،
we can create a robot that is wi-fi enabled
نستطيع عمل روبوت ذو قدرات لاسلكية (ًواي- فاي)
and computer vision-capable for 150 bucks,
ولديه القدرة على الرؤوية بـ 150 دولار،
which is about one percent of what these kinds of robots have cost in the past.
وهي واحد بالمئة مما كلفته هذه الروبوتات في الماضي.
When Romo wakes up, he's in creature mode.
عندما يستيقظ رومو، يكون في وضع المخلوق.
So he's actually using the video camera on the device to follow my face.
يستخدم كاميرة الفيديو في الجهاز لتتبع وجهي.
If I duck down, he'll follow me.
إذا نزلت إلى الأسفل، فهو يلحقني.
He's wary, so he'll keep his eyes on me.
هو حذر، لذلك سيظل يراقبني.
If I come over here, he'll turn to follow me.
إذا جئت هنا، سيلتف ليلحقني.
If I come over here -- (Laughs)
إذا جئت إلى هنا -- (ضحك)
He's smart.
إنه ذكي.
And if I get too close to him,
وإذا اقتربت منه،
he gets scared just like any other creature.
فإنه يخاف مثل أي مخلوق آخر.
So in a lot of ways, Romo is like a pet that has a mind of his own.
لذلك يمكن اعتبار رومو كحيوان أليف لديه عقله الخاص به.
Thanks, little guy.
شكرا، أيها الصبي الصغير.
(Sneezing sound)
(صوت عطسة)
Bless you.
صحة.
And if I want to explore the world -- uh-oh, Romo's tired --
وإذا أردت أن أستكشف العالم -- أوه، رومو متعب --
if I want to explore the world with Romo,
إذا أردت استكشاف العالم
I can actually connect him from any other iOS device.
أستطيع الإتصال معه من أي جهاز يعمل بنظام أبل iOS.
So here's the iPad.
لنأتي بلآيباد.
And Romo will actually stream video to this device.
رومو يستطيع أن يبث الفيديو إلى هذا الجهاز.
So I can see everything that Romo sees,
وبذلك أستطيع رؤوية أي شيء يستطيع رومو رؤيته،
and I get a robot's-eye-view of the world.
والقاء نظرة بعيون الربوت على العالم.
Now this is a free app on the App Store,
هذا هو تطبيق مجاني في متجر البرامج،
so if any of you guys had this app on your phones,
لذا إذا كان أي منكم لديه البرنامج على الهاتف،
we could literally right now share control of the robot and play games together.
يمكننا حرفيا أن نتشارك التحكم بالروبوت ونلعب ألعابا سوية.
So I'll show you really quickly,
لذا سأريكم بسرعة،
Romo actually -- he's streaming video,
رومو -- يبث الفيديو،
so you can see me and the entire TED audience.
لذلك يمكنك رؤويتي ورؤية جميع الحضور في TED.
If I get in front of Romo here.
إذا جئت أمام رومو هنا.
And if I want to control him, I can just drive.
وإذا أردت التحكم به، أستطيع أن أقوده.
So I can drive him around,
لذلك أستطيع أن أقوده هنا وهناك،
and I can take pictures of you.
والتقاط صور لكم.
I've always wanted a picture of a 1,500-person TED audience.
كنت دائما أريد الحصول على صورة لـ 1500 شخص من جمهور TED .
So I'll snap a picture.
لذا سآخذ صورة.
And in the same way that you scroll through content on an iPad,
وبنفس الطريقة التي تستعرض بها المحتوى على الآي باد،
I can actually adjust the angle of the camera on the device.
أستطيع أن أعدل زاوية الكاميرا في الجهاز.
So there are all of you through Romo's eyes.
حتى تصبحوا جميعا مضمنين في عيون رومو.
And finally, because Romo is an extension of me,
وأخيرا، ولأن روموا هو امتداد لي،
I can express myself through his emotions.
أستطيع التعبير عن نفسي من خلال مشاعره.
So I can go in and I can say let's make Romo excited.
لذلك أستطيع الدخول للداخل والقول دعونا نجعل من رومو متحمسا.
But the most important thing about Romo
لكن الشيء الأهم عن رومو
is that we wanted to create something that was literally completely intuitive.
بأننا نريد ايجاد شيء لديه بديهة متكاملة.
You do not have to teach someone how to drive Romo.
لا يجب عليك أن تعلم أحدهم كيف يقود رومو.
In fact, who would like to drive a robot?
في الحقيقة، من يريد أن يقود الروبوت؟
Okay. Awesome.
حسنا. رائع.
Here you go.
تفضل.
Thank you, Scott.
شكرا، سكوت.
And even cooler, you actually don't have to be
وماهو أجمل، بأنه ليس من الضروري
in the same geographic location as the robot to control him.
بأن تكون في نفس المكان الجغرافي للروبت لتتحكم به.
So he actually streams two-way audio and video
لذلك هو في الحقيقة يبث بالإتجاهين الصوت والفيديو
between any two smart devices.
بين أي جهازيين ذكيين.
So you can log in through the browser,
لذلك تستطيع أن تسجل الدخول عبر المتصفح،
and it's kind of like Skype on wheels.
ويمكنك اعتباره وكأنه سكايب على عجلات.
So we were talking before about telepresence,
كنا نتحدث سابقا عن الحضور عن بعد
and this is a really cool example.
وهذا حقا مثال جيد.
You can imagine an eight-year-old girl, for example, who has an iPhone,
يمكنك تخيل فتاة عمرها ثمان سنوات، على سبيل المثال، لديها آي فون،
and her mom buys her a robot.
واشترت لها أمها روبوتا.
That girl can take her iPhone, put it on the robot,
تستطيع الفتاة أخذ الآي فون، وضعه على الروبوت،
send an email to Grandma, who lives on the other side of the country.
ارسال رسال للجدة، والتي تعيش في مكان آخر في البلاد.
Grandma can log into that robot and play hide-and-go-seek with her granddaughter
الجدة تستطيع الدخول إلى الروبوت ولعب لعبة الإختباء مع خفيدتها
for fifteen minutes every single night,
لخمسة عشرة دقيقة في كل ليلة،
when otherwise she might only be able to get to see her granddaughter once or twice a year.
بدون هذا الإختراع، كانت الجدة ترى حفيدتها مرة أو مرتين في السنة.
Thanks, Scott.
شكرا، سكوت.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So those are a couple of the really cool things that Romo can do today.
هناك مجموعة من الأشياء الرائعة التي يستطيع رومو فعلها اليوم.
But I just want to finish by talking about something that we're working on in the future.
وأريد أن أنهي بالكلام عن عن شيء نعمل عليه في المستقبل.
This is actually something that one of our engineers, Dom, built in a weekend.
وهو شيء قام أحد مهندسينا، اسمه دوم, ببناءه في عطلة نهاية الأسبوع.
It's built on top of a Google open framework called Blockly.
إنه مبني على بيئة عمل مفتوحة من غوغل اسمها بلوكلي.
This allows you to drag and drop these blocks of semantic code
وهي تسمح لك بأن تسحب وتفلت قطع الكود
and create any behavior for this robot you want.
وتنشيء أي سلوك تريده لهذا الروبوت.
You do not have to know how to code to create a behavior for Romo.
ليس من الضروري أن تعرف كيف تبرمج لكي تنشيء سلوكا لـرومو.
And you can actually simulate that behavior in the browser,
وتستطيع في الحقيقة محاكاة هذا السلوك في المتصفح،
which is what you see Romo doing on the left.
وهو ماترى رومو يفعله في اليسار.
And then if you have something you like,
وبعد ذلك اذا كان لديك شيء تحبه،
you can download it onto your robot and execute it in real life,
يمكنك تحميله على روبوتك وتنفيذه في الحياة الواقعية,
run the program in real life.
تشغل البرنامج بالحياة الواقعية.
And then if you have something you're proud of,
وإذا كان لديك شيء تفخر به،
you can share it with every other person who owns a robot in the world.
يمكنك مشاركته مع كل شخص يمتكلك هذا الربوت في العالم
So all of these wi-fi–enabled robots actually learn from each other.
إن جميع هذه الروبوتات ذات قدرات الواي-فاي اللاسلكية تتعلم من بعضها.
The reason we're so focused on building robots that everyone can train
السبب الذي يجعلنا مهتمين ببناء روبوتات يستطيع أي أحد تدريبها
is that we think the most compelling use cases in personal robotics are personal.
هو أننا نعتقد بأن أكثر الحالات اقناعا لإستخدام الروبوت الشخصي تكون اسباب شخصية.
They change from person to person.
إنها تتغير من شخص إلى آخر.
So we think that if you're going to have a robot in your home,
لذا نحن نعتقد بأنه إذا كنت تريد الحصول على روبوت في منزلك،
that robot ought to be a manifestation of your own imagination.
هذا الروبوت يجب أن يكون تجسيدا لخيالك.
So I wish that I could tell you what the future of personal robotics looks like.
لذلك أتمنى أن يكون لدي القدرة أن أقول لكم كيف سيبدوا مستقبل الروبوتات الشخصية.
To be honest, I have no idea.
لأكون صريحا، ليس لدي أدنى فكرة.
But what we do know is that it isn't 10 years or 10 billion dollars
لكن مانعرفه هو أنه لن تكون ببعد 10 سنوات أو 10 مليارات دولار
or a large humanoid robot away.
أو ببعد الروبوت على شكل انسان.
The future of personal robotics is happening today,
مستقبل الروبوتات الشخصية يحدث الآن.
and it's going to depend on small, agile robots like Romo
وسوف تعتمد على روبوتات صغيرة، ورشيقة مثل رومو
and the creativity of people like yourselves.
وابداع الأشخاص أمثالك.
So we can't wait to get you all robots,
ونحن نتطلع ان يكون لكل واحد منكم روبوت،
and we can't wait to see what you build.
ونريد أن نرى ماتستطيعون بناءه.
Thank you.
شكرا.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)